Hey,
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): everybody. So on Friday, the New York Times published an article detailing the ways in which Bernie Sanders, in the 1980s, when he was mayor of Vermont, tried to use his office as a platform to influence U.S. foreign policy, which is obviously somewhat novel for a mayor to do, especially a mayor of a relatively small city. The mayor of New York City always uses his office.
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): platform to have some effect on U.S. foreign policy, especially as it relates to Israel, because, you know, there's a large
Speaker 2: Jewish population in New York, and that's just commonplace. Bill de Blasio does it. Mike Bloomberg did it.
But for the mayor of
Speaker 2: Burlington and Vermont
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): to do it, it was a little bit unusual. And some of the information in the article is
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): actually genuinely interesting, especially if you're not familiar with that history.
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): I actually was familiar with much of it because in 2015 I
Speaker 5: spent some time in the archive at the University of Vermont in Burlington,
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): which houses the papers and records from Bernie's mayoral tenure. And there's a lot of really fascinating stuff in there, even dating back to his pre-mayoral days when he was...
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): Basically, on the fringes of politics in the state, he ran
as a
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): third-party candidate for different offices, the Liberty Union Party. It was a very interesting platform. And I wrote about it at the time, you know, during the previous
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): electoral cycle. I might at some point actually go back and look through some of those documents that I found and write something new.
But
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): the New York Times just discovered this somehow, and
so they
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): did this article
Speaker 6: where, although, again, some interesting information was presented, it was
Speaker 5: obviously framed in such a way as to depict his activities of the 80s as unserious,
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): perhaps even disqualifying, at the very least a big political liability. So,
for
Speaker 5: example,
Speaker 5: In 1985, Bernie traveled to Managua in Nicaragua and
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): met with Daniel Ortega, who is now the leader of Nicaragua. And basically Bernie made it very clear that he was opposed to the foreign policy
Speaker 7: under Ronald Reagan, which the CIA was deployed.
Speaker 7: to basically oust the government. And
Speaker 5: Bernie said, arguably Bernie expressed sympathy with the Nicaraguan government.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): And he lamented that the American media had quote, not reflected fairly the goals and accomplishments of your administration.
and
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): that the media wasn't reporting the truth
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): about Ortega. And my favorite line from the article is when
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): Sanders
seethed at one
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): of the journalists that accompanied him on this trip.
His name
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): was George Creel from CBS. And Sanders said to Creel, quote, You are worms.
And
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): Bernie's always had some of a cantankerous relationship with media. He doesn't like a lot of them. He
doesn't like
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): a lot of journalists. He thinks that they're often focused on the wrong things or they're just trying to get soundbites or they're not interested in substance, which, you know, is largely true. So
I don't
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): blame him for being cantankerous and having an inbred or inborn suspicion of especially elite journalists who...
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): often like to depict him as some kind of,
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): you know, raging leftist or whatever, which I mean, he is to some extent, but, you know, he's a social democrat, he wouldn't be outside of the mainstream in many countries in the world. But now, you know, the New York Times
is
Speaker 5: basically saying that
Bernie is
Speaker 5: going to have to account for the fact that.
Speaker 5: You know, he was somehow a huge fan of the Sandinistas in the 80s. And the
New York Times
Speaker 5: doesn't really bother to mention how disastrous the Reagan foreign policy was in Central America. In fact, arguably, the destabilization that the Reagan foreign policy wrought in that region, you can trace that
to the...
The
Speaker 5: instability right now in Central America, which is leading to these refugees and other migrants fleeing
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): north to the U.S. and coming trying to get across the border. Obviously, it's been a while,
so it's not a
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): tight correlation there necessarily, but, you know, it wasn't like 200 years ago. It was a few
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): decades ago.
And these
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): kinds of regime change policies have a long-lasting impact on
the
Speaker 2: societies in which those policies are carried out. So I don't think it's too much of a stretch. But, you know, they go through some of the history where, you know, various residents of Burlington were getting
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): fed up with Bernie devoting a lot of his mayoral energies into dealing with foreign policy, which again was fairly unorthodox.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): They quote one Burlington resident as writing to Bernie, writing in a letter to the editor in 1986, quote, he's not even running for governor, he's running for foreign minister. Bernie ran for governor of Vermont that year and lost. And
I actually
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): think it's laudable that Bernie would have devoted so much of his attention to foreign policy so long as he was able to keep municipal functions going, which by all accounts he was. I mean, he was actually...
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): Pretty widely regarded for his ability to just have basic services function
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): adequately. So, you know, paving roads, you
know, sewage
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): systems, that kind of thing. So
he kind of
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): governs in Burlington sort of as a pragmatist in that respect. But, you know, he also did stuff that's depicted in the New York Times as very
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): suspicious, such as formalizing a sister city relationship in 1988,
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): Between Burlington and Garoslavl, I hope I'm pronouncing that right, which was a city in the Soviet Union and on the Volga River. And he, of course, traveled there
with a Soviet
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): delegation just weeks before the gubernatorial election that year. Or rather, weeks before the...
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): House race that he ran for in 1988, which he also didn't win So Bernie actually, you know, people might not remember this, Bernie actually lost quite a few graces in the early part of his career When he ran for different offices on the Liberty Union ticket, he got like single digits so He has some familiarity with losing but
but
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): it was perfectly viable for him to want to forge closer ties with the Soviet Union, especially in this era, which was the era of an opening under Gorbachev. I mean, Republicans were
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): encouraging this at the time. That's why they embraced Gorbachev.
So
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): the idea that it's like obviously the marker of ideological extremism for him to take in these
Speaker 7: kind of anodyne diplomatic steps with regard to
Speaker 7: The Soviet Union is silly.
And in remarks
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): captured on an audio recording, the New York Times Moe dramatically relays, Bernie is quoted as saying, the cost of services
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): is much, much higher in the United States. He's talking about medical care. And he says in the Soviet Union, health care is free or virtually free. That's true. Bernie wasn't saying that health care in the Soviet Union is...
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): He's not exceptionally good in every circumstance, but he's correct that it didn't cost anything, or not nearly as much as it does in the U.S. That's just a statement of fact.
But when he was running for the
Speaker 6: House, he made foreign policy actually a big
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): issue. He
said he wanted
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): to, quote, reduce the obscene federal military budget.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): He said that there are certain aspects of the Cuban approach to governance that he thought were laudable, even if it was not perfect. So,
I mean,
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): none of this should be surprising for anybody who's remotely familiar with Bernie. But nonetheless, I mean, if you're not acquainted with some of that from the Burlington years, it is kind of interesting to read through.
You
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): know, one thing that they put out is that Sanders distributed a pamphlet in 1982 saying your vote can help stop another Vietnam because
he was
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): calling on the U.S.
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): to stop propping up the dictatorship in El Salvador. And he actually backed a ballot initiative that
year.
And
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): basically just to register Burlington's opposition to U.S. involvement in that country, which,
you know,
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): municipalities do do on occasion during the Iraq war. A lot of localities passed resolutions opposing it, but, you know, it doesn't actually have a huge real world impact. It's just sort of symbolic, but, you know, symbolism matters in a way. So
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): I think
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): it was
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): viable for him to do this, considering how...
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): overzealous, to say the least, the Reagan administration was and overthrowing governments and installing their little puppet regimes in Central America and elsewhere. And
Bernie
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): was on Meet the Press today and Chuck Todd basically asked him if he regretted his anti-war activism with regard to Vietnam. It's just like, are you kidding? Why doesn't Chuck Todd
ask...
people who
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): weren't opposed to the Vietnam War, why they didn't do anything to oppose it, given how utterly disastrous it was. I mean, I have a book on my shelf
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): right now. It's called Kill Anything That Moves by Nick Terse. And
you got
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): to read this book. I mean, even if you think that you know the history of the Vietnam War, you don't know how systematically brutal...
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): and how targeted it was at actually killing civilians, again, in a systematic way. It wasn't just the My Lai Massacre. Everybody knows about the My Lai Massacre because it was extremely egregious, but just
on a more
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): mundane day-to-day level, the amount of civilian death that was inflicted by the U.S. is just staggering.
And of course,
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): you know, over 50,000 U.S. troops
died.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): veterans dealing even now with Agent Orange and other disabilities. So, I mean, that entire American involvement in Southeast Asia was just utterly disastrous. So for Chuck Todd to be pretending as though it's somehow outside the mainstream to have opposed the Vietnam War, or it's like shameful, that's shameful for Chuck Todd to suggest. I mean, he's kind of not...
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): especially adroit person if that's the line of questioning that he's going with. But anyway, Bernie originally didn't
Speaker 5: respond to requests for comment about the New York Times article. But
I guess
Speaker 5: the day after it was published, he did get in touch with Sidney Ember, who's one of the reporters. And he
had a
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): very contentious interview, and a lot of people were complaining, oh, Bernie was so rude, how dare
he?
The
Speaker 5: special snowflake New York Times reporter shouldn't be subject to his rudeness. And it's just like, no, she deserved it. Bernie should have been ruder, frankly. I'm actually impressed that he managed to restrain himself. He did, but they get into...
They get
Speaker 5: into...
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): I mean, one
of the questions that
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): Sidney Ember asks him, and you can read this interview, I'll post
it,
Is at
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): the top of the story, she says we talk about the rally you attended in Managua and a wire report at the time that said there were anti-American chants from the crowd. I mean, gee, why would there be anti-American chants in the crowd when they're trying to overthrow the government by funding a death militia?
But Bernie
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): responds, the United States at the time, I don't know how much you know about this, was actively...
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): supporting the Contras to overthrow the government. So there's anti-America sentiment. I remember that. I remember that event very clearly.
And she follows up
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): with him. You recall hearing those chants? Oh, my God. How horrible. There could have been some mean chants going on.
And he
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): says, they were fighting against American. Ha, ha, yes. What's your point?
Are you
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): shocked to learn that there was anti-American sentiment?
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): and then she follows up
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): saying do you think if you had heard that directly meaning the chant you would have stayed at the rally and he says I think Sidney with all due respect you
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): don't understand a word I'm saying and he says you know stuff like that repeatedly and you know there are people whining that this means that like Bernie's like Trump or something and he's like demeaning the press
Speaker 5: it's like sometimes the press deserves to be demeaned because they
ask
Speaker 5: idiotic questions. You're not immune from criticism because you happen to be a reporter at
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): the New York Times. In fact, you deserve extra criticism given the influence of that role. So, I mean, this is just totally in keeping with
Speaker 7: Bernie's persona
where he
Speaker 7: rightly finds it annoying when people ask him dumb questions just like anybody would. Sidney Ember actually
Speaker 7: is prone to confabulating controversies about Bernie out of thin air. You may remember that in January, she wrote a piece basically alleging that the Bernie Sanders 2016 campaign was like this hotbed of sexist abuse, and how could Bernie not have known that people were being abused? And one of the big scandals
Speaker 2: was that some woman volunteer of Bernie's
She had
Speaker 2: lodging
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): arrangements in Illinois, I think it was, that she didn't like. And so, like, put in a request to get it changed and got it changed. But that was, like, sexist abuse or something that Bernie was enabling. It was so stupid. It was obviously just designed to kneecap him before he actually announced his campaign and it didn't work.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): Anyway, I think on one level it's good that these malignant reporters are trying to badger Bernie on foreign policy in particular because it forces him to adhere to his long-standing
Speaker 5: principles because consistency
is one of his
Speaker 5: biggest political assets. It's why so many people like him, that he just says the same thing over and over again and has for decades, almost
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): to the point of tedium.
But
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): nonetheless, he says
the same
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): stuff over and over again. And they like that he's consistent. So by bringing up these old statements and these old actions that he took
Speaker 5: in the 80s, it
kind of places an
Speaker 5: incentive on Bernie that in order to preserve his consistency, he has to assertively stand by and
not apologize
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): for these old statements.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): notwithstanding how they could be twisted by his enemies.
So I
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): think that's actually a positive thing militating on Bernie right now, because if he's trying to ingratiate himself with elements of the Democratic establishment, there's obviously a risk or, you know, he could be inclined to jettison some of those
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): old principles because, you know, they could be seen as a big political liability.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): and it plays into why
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): He ended up more or lessing towing the he ended up towing more or less the mainstream Democratic line on Trump, Russia, which
I still
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): think is a big blunder and a blemish for him. But on this stuff, on this issue in particular, you know, the regime change in Central America, he was right. He was basically entirely right in the 80s and he's right now. So anyway, I think he was
Speaker 5: right to be ornery with this.
Speaker 5: reporter who who who deserves it and then some
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): and i think you know bernie actually uh he comported himself well here um i have criticisms of bernie on different issues but i like to think that they're in good faith i've always said i have a broad affinity with him i voted for him in 2016 doesn't mean i'm a bernie you know fanboy i can criticize where necessary
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): Um, uh, but you know, this is when he's in top form when he's just at war with horrible people in the media in particular and defending a principle that he subscribed to for decades, which is obviously right. Um,
and you
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): know, hopefully maybe there'll be more of this going forward. We shall see. Anyway, I'll link to some of that in the description box and have a good night, everybody. I'm not going to be watching game of Thrones. So I hope if you are, I hope your preferred goblin wins or whatever. Uh, but other than that, talk to you later.